I hope you all are doing very well.
आशा करता हूं आप सब बहुत अच्छे होंगे।
My name is Siddhant Agnihotri.
मेरा नाम है सिद्धांत अग्निहोत्री। स्टडी
Welcome to Study Gloss.
ग्लोस पे आपका बहुत-बहुत स्वागत है।
Rajnath Singh has said two very important things.
राजनाथ सिंह ने दो बहुत बड़ी बातें बोली
Firstly, he has said that
हैं। पहली उन्होंने बोली है बोला है कि अ
Pakistan will have to face very serious
पाकिस्तान जो है उसको बहुत ही भारी
consequences.  We will
कॉन्सिक्वेंसेस झेलने पड़ेंगे। हम
destroy Pakistan if Pakistan
पाकिस्तान को तबाह कर देंगे अगर पाकिस्तान
attacks now.  And secondly he has said that
ने अब हमला किया। और दूसरा उन्होंने बोला
Operation Sindoor is still going on.  So
है ऑपरेशन सिंदूर अभी भी जारी है। तो
we will look at both things.  Let me tell you
दोनों ही चीजों को हम देखेंगे। बता दूं
friends that you can avail our wonderful course which is a
दोस्तों कि हमारा जो शानदार कोर्स है
combo of Chanakya Niti and Personality Development.  You will
कॉम्बो उसको आप अेल कर सकते हैं। आपको
benefit a lot.  So friends
बहुत ज्यादा फायदा होगा। तो दोस्तों इसका
what does this mean?  What is happening now?  What is
मतलब क्या है? अभी क्या हो रहा है? अभी यह
happening now is that America and Pakistan are
हो रहा है कि अमेरिका और पाकिस्तान ढिंका
doing Dhinkha Chika together.  Both the countries are
चिका साथ में कर रहे हैं। दोनों ही देश जो
developing very good relations with each other.  Now Operation Sindoor has happened and
बना रहे हैं। अब ऑपरेशन सिंदूर हुआ और
you have heard from every leader that
आपने हर एक नेता से यह बात सुनी है कि
Operation Sindoor is still
ऑपरेशन सिंदूर जो है वो अभी इट इज स्टिल
going on.  what does this mean friend?
गोइंग ऑन। इसका मतलब क्या है यार? इसका
What does it mean?  One meaning of this could be
मतलब क्या है? इसका मतलब एक तो यह हो सकता
that we are still killing terrorists selectively.
है कि अभी भी हम आतंकवादियों को चुन चुन
Secondly it could be that
के मार रहे हैं। दूसरा यह हो सकता है कि
we have put it on hold for now.  Actually,
अभी हमने इसको होल्ड किया है। एक्चुअल में
we have
क्या है ना कि हमारे पास कोई हमने कोई
not received any result regarding this.  The result was that
रिजल्ट नहीं आया इसका। रिजल्ट ये आया कि
Pakistan was in trouble and
पाकिस्तान की बैंड बजी और पाकिस्तान ने
its DGMO called.  No cease fire
कॉल किया उनके डीजीएमओ ने। कोई सीज फायर
agreement has been signed.  Nothing.   It has
एग्रीमेंट साइन नहीं हुआ है। कुछ भी नहीं।
just been discussed that it is on hold, so it
बस बात हुई है कि होल्ड पे है तो इसका
means Operation Sindoor is still going on.  If
मतलब ऑपरेशन सिंदूर अभी भी चल रहा है। अगर
India attacks then no country can say anything
भारत हमला कर दे तो कोई देश नहीं बोल सकता
because we can tell that my brother,
क्योंकि हम बता सकते हैं कि मेरे भाई
Operation Sindoor is still going on and
ऑपरेशन सिंदूर अभी भी और शिमला एग्रीमेंट
we have not signed any agreement like Shimla Agreement.
जो है वो हमने कोई एग्रीमेंट साइन नहीं
So that is why every leader is saying this
किया। तो इसीलिए हर एक नेता यही बोल रहा
and everyone is saying this.  In fact,
है और हर कोई ये बोल रहा है। इनफैक्ट
our army, our
हमारे जो आर्मी है वो उनके भी आप जो हमारे
Chief of Defence, Anil Chauhan was also saying
चीफ ऑफ डिफेंस वो भी अनिल चौहान भी ये बोल
that Operation Sindoor is still
रहे थे कि ऑपरेशन सिंदूर जो है वो अभी भी
going on.  Ok?  And the third thing
चल ही रहा है। ठीक है? और तीसरा यह हो
could be that India is planning something big to
सकता है कि इंडिया जो है वह बहुत बड़ी कुछ
enter India and
प्लानिंग कर रहा है भारत में घुस के कुछ
do something.  So what do you think out of the three
करने की। तो आपको क्या लगता है तीनों में
or if you have any other point then please
से या अगर आपके पास कोई और पॉइंट हो तो आप
tell me.  Then after that Rajnath
मुझे जरूर बताइएगा। फिर उसके बाद राजनाथ
Singh has said one more thing that terrible
सिंह ने एक और चीज बोली है कि भयानक
consequences will have to be faced.  See where
क्सकेंसेस उठाने पड़ेंगे। देखिए जहां पे
terrible consequences will happen.  Where the
भयानक कंसक्वेंसेस होंगे। जहां पे
Defence Minister of Pakistan,
पाकिस्तान का जो डिफेंस मिनिस्टर है
Khawaja Asif, it is absolutely certain that
ख्वाजा आसिफ ये बात बिल्कुल पक्की है कि
he speaks anything after taking cheap drugs, he
वो सस्ता नशा करके बोलता है कुछ भी बोलता
himself accepts defeat, accepts defeat, he
है खुद ही हार लेता है हार मान लेता है
himself tells everything, we need to do more, that
खुद ही बता देता है सब कुछ हमको ज्यादा
Khawaja Asif also likes to say that
कुछ करने की वो ख्वाजा आसिफ भी लाइक कि
brother, if there are people like you, then here it
भैया तुम्हारे जैसे लोग हो तो हमारे यहां
means that there is no need for an enemy,
तो मतलब वही है कि दुश्मन की जरूरत नहीं
you alone are enough, so he is telling that
है तुम ही काफी हो अकेले तो वही बता रहे
that man is strange and our
हैं ना कि वो आदमी अजीब है और हमारे
Defence Minister speaks very carefully
डिफेंस मिनिस्टर जो हैं वो बहुत ही नापतोल
but whatever he says has a
के बात करते हैं लेकिन जो वो बोलते हैं
meaning, a deeper meaning,
उसका मीनिंग होता है एक डीपर मीनिंग होता
so what does it mean, this also
है तो इसका मतलब क्या है यह भी पाकिस्तान
gave a clear message to Pakistan and this
को साफ-साफ संदेश दिया और यह बहुत ही
timing is very right because Asim Munir has
टाइमिंग सही है क्योंकि आसिम मुनीर जो हैं
again gone to America and sung the Bharat Labh Bharat
उसने फिर जाके अमेरिका में भारत लाभ भारत
Raag and there is hatred against India,
राग अलापा है और भारत के खिलाफ नफरत जो है
in his speech, he had invited very few
उसने अपनी स्पीच में जो इन्होंने बहुत कम
Pakistanis and
पाकिस्तानियों को बुलाया था और वहां पे ये
when I saw this speech there, although its
स्पीच जब मैंने देखी हालांकि इसके जो
bytes are not properly available,
बाइट्स थे वो तो प्रॉपर अवेलेबल नहीं है
but many news articles had covered it, so a
लेकिन बहुत सारे न्यूज़ आर्टिकल्स ने कवर
lot of hatred against India was
किया था तो भारत के खिलाफ काफी जो है वो
spewed there as well.
नफरत उगली वहां पे भी उगली और बाहरी जो है
Many slogans were also raised by the outsiders that the
वो काफी नारे भी लगे कि इस्लामाबाद का
killer of Islamabad, Asim Munir, well this is one
कातिल जो है आसिम मुनीर ठीक तो एक तो ये
and after that Donald Trump made him have
तो और उसके बाद फिर डॉनल्ड ट्रंप ने इसको
lunch and fed him.  This report is coming,
लंच करवाया खानावाना खिलाया। रिपोर्ट ये आ
I am not sure.  But it is also being said
रही है आई एम नॉट श्योर। लेकिन ये भी कहा
that Iran has used the basis of Pakistan.
जा रहा है कि पाकिस्तान के बेसिस का यूज़
See, Pakistan has broken the spine of
किया है ईरान। देखिए पाकिस्तान ने स्पाइन
Iran.  You should assume this.
की है ईरान की। आप यह मान के चलिए।
Pakistan has given a strong spine to Iran.
पाकिस्तान ने तगड़ी स्पाइन की है ईरान की।
Iran has been stabbed in the back, which was
ईरान के पीठ में खंजर भोंका है जो कि उनसे
expected from them because everyone says this.
एक्सपेक्टेड था क्योंकि ये हर कोई बोलता
Including Donald Trump has said
है। इंक्लूडिंग डोनल्ड ट्रंप बोल चुके हैं
that you cannot trust Pakistan.
कि आप पाकिस्तान के ऊपर भरोसा नहीं कर
So where America and Pakistan are
सकते। तो जहां पे अमेरिका और पाकिस्तान
coming very close, they have again
काफी क्लोज आ रहे हैं तो उन्होंने फिर से
told India that we should forget the Indus Water Treaty.
बोला है भारत ने कि हम इंडस वाटर ट्रीटी
Amit Shah even said that
भूल जाओ। अमित शाह ने तो बोला कि जब
we will sign the Indus Water Treaty only when Pakistan stops terrorism.
पाकिस्तान टेररिज्म रोकेगा तभी हम इंडस
Ok?  So Pakistan is
वाटर ट्रीटी करेंगे। ठीक है? तो इंडस वाटर
not getting water from the Indus Water Treaty anyway.
ट्रीटी पानी तो वैसे भी नहीं मिल रहा
So forget that and
पाकिस्तान को। तो वो तो आप भूल जाइए और
whatever you do after that, if you
उसके बाद आप कुछ भी करोगे अगर आपने जरा सा
miss the adventure even a little, you will
भी मिस एडवेंचर किया तो आपको खामियाजा
have to suffer the consequences.  Now look at this, there
भुगतना पड़ेगा। अब ऐसा देखिए ईरान में
is instability in Iran and India is suffering loss due to this.
अनस्टेबिलिटी है और इसमें भारत को नुकसान
Why is there a loss?  Because many
है। क्यों नुकसान है? क्योंकि बहुत सारे
militant groups can come to Pakistan and
मिलिटेंट ग्रुप्स पाकिस्तान आ सकते हैं और
then create problems in India also.
फिर भारत में भी प्रॉब्लम फैला सकते हैं।
Especially in Kashmir and Pakistan
स्पेशली कश्मीर में और इसमें पाकिस्तान
can help them in this.  Now see, India has
उनकी मदद कर सकता है। अब देखिए भारत ने
clearly told America and
अमेरिका को भी साफ-साफ बोल दिया डॉनल्ड
Narendra Modi has also told Donald Trump that
ट्रंप को भी बोल दिया नरेंद्र मोदी ने कि
you did not stop our war and stop saying this.
आपने हमारा वॉर नहीं रुकवाया और यह बोलना
But still, he keeps speaking continuously.
बंद करिए। लेकिन फिर भी वो लगातार बोले जा
I have told many times that Donald Trump's behaviour is narcissism
मैंने कई बार बताया कि नार्सिसिज्म है
and Pakistan has understood that very
उनको और वो समझ लिया है पाकिस्तान ने बहुत
well.  Ok?  And India also
बढ़िया तरीके से। ठीक है? और भारत ने भी
understood this.  India was also taking decisions accordingly.
ये समझा था। भारत भी उसी हिसाब से डिसीजन
He was nominated for the Nobel Peace Prize.
ले रहा था। नोबेल पीस प्राइज के लिए इनको
Benjamin is
नॉमिनेट कर दिया। बेंजामिन नेतालिया होप
praising Natalia Hope Don Trump so much that
डॉन्ड ट्रंप की इतनी तारीफ कर रहे हैं कि
your name will be written in golden words.  So Donald
आपका नाम लिखा जाएगा। तो इस समय डोनल्ड
Trump is very happy right now.  He is very happy.
ट्रंप बहुत खुश है। बहुत ज्यादा खुश है।
Ok?  And because then Pakistan is accepting everything he
ठीक है? और क्योंकि फिर पाकिस्तान हर उनकी
says.  So this is a matter of
बात मान रहा है। तो ये भारत के लिए कहीं
concern for India.  That is why
ना कहीं चिंताजनक है। इसलिए भारत साफ
India has said in clear words that if you
शब्दों में भारत ने बोला है कि देखो तुम
come, we will not let you go this time.   Is it
आओगे तो जाने नहीं देंगे तुमको इस बार।
okay?  We will search and kill you.
ठीक है ना? ढूंढ-ढूंढ के मारेंगे। एक और
Friends another news is about Pahalgam attack that it is being said
दोस्तों खबर यह है पहलगांव हमले से कि कहा
that whatever I was reading in Indian Express,
जा रहा है कि जो ये इंडियन एक्सप्रेस में
I will cover that too, I will
पढ़ रहा था उसका उस पे भी मैं कवर कवर
bring a lecture that the sketches were
करूंगा लेक्चर लाऊंगा एक कि जो स्केच थे
made wrongly and not a single terrorist
वो गलत बनाए गए और जो आतंकी थे उसप एक भी
was local.  Now this raises very big questions.
लोकल नहीं था। अब ये बहुत बड़े-बड़े सवाल
We will talk about this also.
खड़े करता है। इसकी भी हम बात करेंगे।
But for now, this is a direct warning from Rajnath Singh
लेकिन फिलहाल यह राजनाथ सिंह की सीधा-सीधा
to Pakistan.  So maybe
पाकिस्तान को चेतावनी है। तो इसलिए शायद
you will see that Pakistan does
आप देखें कि यह पाकिस्तान टेररिस्ट हमला
not carry out terrorist attacks.  Because even now if you see,
ना करें। क्योंकि अभी भी अगर आपने देखा तो
in the Pahalgam attack he did not accept the responsibility and said, no
पहलगांव हमले में उसने जिम्मेदारी से
we did not do it.
बिल्कुल कि नहीं हमने तो किया नहीं। उसके
Despite that we killed you because we know
बावजूद हमने तुमको मारा क्योंकि हमको पता
where terrorism came from.  So now if it
है कि कहां से आतंकवाद आया है। तो अब अगर
happens next time then you can understand
अगली बार होता है तो आप समझ लीजिए कि इसका
what its scale will be.  How big can it be?
स्केल कितना होगा। कितना बड़ा हो सकता है।
Ok?  So this was a small lecture, an analysis.
ओके? तो ये छोटा सा लेक्चर था, एनालिसिस
Be happy, keep reading.  This is
था। खुश रहिए, पढ़ते रहिए। दिस इज
Siddhant signing off.
सिद्धांत साइनिंग ऑफ।